A Guide to the James C. V. Emond Papers, 1857-1988
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
James C. V. Emond Papers, 1857-1988
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1991-026
3.4 cu. ft. 7 boxes
Papers--including printed materials, correspondence, research notes, photographs, and ephemera--collected by James C. V. Emond, pastor of Fairlawn Church of Christ (Galax, Virginia), while researching the history of his church and the surrounding community.
Emond, James C. V.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The James C. V. Emond Papers were purchased by Special Collections in 1991.
Biographical Note
James C. V. Emond was born in Indiana on December 17, 1927, the son of Elmer Emond of Seattle Washington. After serving in the military during World War II, Emond moved to Washington state, where he married Barbara Mae Hughes in 1951. From 1967 to 1974, Emond served as pastor of Fairlawn Church of Christ (Galax, Virginia). In the latter year, he received a master's degree in religion from Emmanuel School of Religion (Johnson City, Tennessee). James Emond died on June 16, 1989, and was buried at Union Christian Church Cemetery, Larue County, Kentucky.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains papers--including newspaper clippings, correspondence, photographs, and notes--of James C. V. Emond, pastor of the Fairlawn Church of Christ (Galax, Virginia) from 1967 to 1974. Most of the collection consists of materials assembled by Emond while researching the history of his church, together with a larger project looking at the church's history within the context of local settlement and development. The collection consists largely of photocopies of original sources but also includes some original materials, perhaps the most significant of these being the papers of local residents Braselton B. Frost and Early A. Goodson.
Arrangement
Emond's papers were originally arranged in Dewey Decimal system order. While Emond's file titles largely remain intact (some additions being made with materials found loose in the collection), the folders have been rearranged in a generally alphabetical order. Materials relating strictly to Fairlawn Church of Christ have been separated from Emond's research on the surrounding area, thus creating the following two series:
Series I. Fairlawn Church of Christ Research, 1857-1985. This series contains files relating strictly to Fairlawn Church of Christ (Galax, Virginia). Included are correspondence, research notes, and photocopies of records relating to membership, pastors, property, and other aspects of the church's history. The series also contains drafts of Emond's two works on the church's history.
Series II. Contextual Research, 1878-1988. Contained in this series are materials assembled by Emond while conducting broader research into the history and development of Galax, Carroll County, Grayson County, and southwestern Virginia. The series consists largely of newspaper clippings and other printed materials. Some of the files, however, contain original materials donated to or purchased by Emond. Among these are the papers of Braselton B. Frost and Early A. Goodson. The photographs in the series, many dating to the late 19th or early 20th century, also consist of originals. The files cover a broad range of subjects. Particularly strong are files devoted to churches and Galax's Old Fiddlers' Convention. A number of files in the series are devoted to a particular individual or family, with a strong emphasis on the Cooley and Cox families.
Some of the file titles in the collection bear two separate date ranges. These folders contain photocopies or transcriptions of significant original documents and records. The dates in [brackets] refer to the date range of the original items.
Index Terms
Geographical Names:
Carroll County (Va.); Galax (Va.); Grayson County (Va.)
Subjects:
Local/Regional History and Appalachian South
Contents List
- Series I. Fairlawn Church of Christ Research, 1857-1985
  - Anecdotes and scandals, 1974, n.d. (Box-folder 1-1)
  - Bible school, 1969, n.d. (Box-folder 1-2)
  - Blue Ridge District Convention [1903-1933], n.d., [2 folders] (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Financial reports, 1964-1973 (Box-folder 1-4)
  - Interview notes, 1969-1981, n.d. (Box-folder 1-5)
  - Membership records, 1960-1969, n.d. (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Ministers, 1969-1985, n.d. (Box-folder 1-7)
  - Programs, 1968-1983 (Box-folder 1-8-9)
  - Property and building, 1931-1969, n.d. (Box-folder 1-10)
  - Revivals, 1980-1983, n.d. (Box-folder 1-11)
  - Stewardship [1929-1981], 1981, n.d. (Box-folder 1-12)
  - Notes, printed material and ephemera, 1857-1981, n.d. (Box-folder 1-13)
  - Research notecards, ca. 1969 (Box-folder 2-1)
  - "History of the Fairlawn Church of Christ" first draft, 1969 (Box-folder 2-2)
  - "History of Fairlawn Church of Christ" typed draft, 1969 (Box-folder 2-3)
  - "Some Backgrounds to a History of Fairlawn Church of Christ" drafts, 1976, [2 folders] (Box-folder 2-4)
- Series II. Contextual Research, 1878-1988
  - Alderman, John, 1973-1981 (Box-folder 2-5)
  - Allen family, 1960-1984, n.d. (Box-folder 2-6)
  - Archaeology, 1971-1975, n.d. (Box-folder 2-7)
  - Baker, Kylene (Miss America, 1979), 1978-1984 (Box-folder 2-8)
  - Book acquisitions, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 2-9)
  - Branscombe family, 1966-1973, n.d. (Box-folder 2-10)
  - Bullard, Chester, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 2-11)
  - Burcham, Carnie Roy, 1972-1974 (Box-folder 2-12)
  - Carroll County, Virginia Financial Report and Directory, 1934-1974 (Box-folder 2-13-3-3)
  - Churches
    - General materials, 1973-1985 (Box-folder 3-4)
    - Baptist, 1960-1985, n.d., [2 folders] (Box-folder 3-5)
    - Christian Church and Church of Christ, 1976-1978 (Box-folder 3-6)
    - Coulson Church of the Brethren, 1973 (Box-folder 3-7)
    - First Christian Church (Galax), 1974-1984, n.d. (Box-folder 3-8)
    - Hebron Church of Christ, 1973-1977 (Box-folder 3-9)
    - Hillsville Christian Church, 1973-1986, n.d. (Box-folder 3-10)
    - Locust Grove Church of Christ, 1973-1982 (Box-folder 3-11)
    - Methodist, 1950-1985 (Box-folder 3-12)
    - Moravian, 1974, n.d. (Box-folder 3-13)
    - Mt. Pisgah, 1973, n.d. (Box-folder 3-14)
    - Pleasant Hill (Old Town), n.d. (Box-folder 3-15)
    - Presbyterian, 1917-1976, n.d. (Box-folder 3-16)
    - Primitive Baptist, 1969-1987, n.d. (Box-folder 3-17)
    - Quaker, 1970-1985, n.d. (Box-folder 3-18)
    - River Hill Christian Church, 1985-1986, n.d. (Box-folder 3-19)
    - Sylvatus Christian Church, 1950-1973, n.d. (Box-folder 4-1)
  - Civil War, 1974-1987, n.d. (Box-folder 4-2)
  - Coal Creek, 1988, n.d. (Box-folder 4-3)
  - Cole, Willie R., 1973-1979 (Box-folder 4-4)
  - Communities, 1971-1985, n.d. (Box-folder 4-5)
  - Cooley, Amanda J., 1980, n.d. (Box-folder 4-6)
  - Cooley, Elbert M. and Elmer J., 1955-1964, n.d. (Box-folder 4-7)
  - Cooley, Elizabeth Ann, n.d. (Box-folder 4-8)
  - Cooley, Julia Ann, n.d. (Box-folder 4-9)
  - Cooley, William Rufus [1856-1973], 1973, n.d. (Box-folder 4-10)
  - Cooley family - General, 1973-1987, n.d. (Box-folder 4-11)
  - County formation and administration, 1974-1976, n.d. (Box-folder 4-12)
  - Courthouse - Carroll County, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 4-13)
  - Courthouse - Grayson County, 1976-1988 (Box-folder 4-14)
  - Cox, Grace, 1969 (Box-folder 4-15)
  - Cox family, 1973-1975, n.d. (Box-folder 5-1)
  - Crawford, Mack, 1974, n.d. (Box-folder 5-2)
  - Crimes and disasters, 1971-1988 (Box-folder 5-3)
  - Dial, Helen and James, 1970-1976 (Box-folder 5-4)
  - Emond, James C. V., 1970-1974 (Box-folder 5-5)
  - "Footprints on the Sands of Time" newspaper column, 1974 (Box-folder 5-6)
  - Frost, Braselton B., 1878-1973, n.d. (Box-folder 5-7)
  - Galax, 1956-1983, n.d. (Box-folder 5-8)
  - Goad, Byrum Perry, 1973-1981 (Box-folder 5-9)
  - Goodson, Early A., 1928-1956, n.d. (Box-folder 5-10)
  - Guynn, Jack, 1974-1979 (Box-folder 5-11)
  - Hawks, Reeves V., n.d. (Box-folder 5-12)
  - Historical societies, 1973-1982 (Box-folder 5-13)
  - Industry and economic development, 1973-1985 (Box-folder 5-14)
  - Ku Klux Klan march, n.d. (Box-folder 5-15)
  - Landreth, J. J. and Sidna F., 1974-1977 (Box-folder 5-16)
  - Language and dialect, 1974-1979 (Box-folder 5-17)
  - Larrowe, Heath, 1973-1978, n.d. (Box-folder 5-18)
  - Lincoln, Nancy Hanks, 1974, n.d. (Box-folder 5-19)
  - Lineberry, 1973-1986, n.d. (Box-folder 5-20)
  - Maps, 1965-1973, n.d. (Box-folder 5-21)
  - Mills, 1970-1978 (Box-folder 5-22)
  - Music and musicians, 1971-1984 (Box-folder 5-23)
  - Newspapers, 1956-1986, n.d. (Box-folder 5-24)
  - Obituaries and biographical material, 1946-1988, n.d. (Box-folder 5-25)
  - "Odds and Ends from Now and Then" newspaper column, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 5-26)
  - Old Fiddlers' Convention, 1972-1987 (Box-folder 6-1)
  - Photographs, 1914-1973, n.d., [2 folders] (Box-folder 6-2)
    - First Fairlawn wedding (Dotson-Trimble), n.d., [photocopy]
    - Coleman School, 1914-1915
    - N. A. Cox home, 1973
    - Lynch Calfee home, 1973, [2 items]
    - Vera Lyons Robinson home, 1973
    - Chimney remains of Nancy Hanks cabin, [1973?]
    - Heath Larrowe place, 1973, [4 items]
    - 150-year old oak tree in Galax, 1973
    - Remains of Grassy Creek meeting house, 1973
    - Mr. and Mrs. S. L. Hoffman, n.d.
    - Mr. and Mrs. Isom Melton, n.d.
    - Baptisms, 1938-1947, [5 items]
    - Pump organ used in tabernacle, n.d.
    - Carl Bowles and others, 1962
    - Jack Sanders and others, 1964
    - J. Watson Shockley, n.d.
    - N. A. Cox, n.d.
    - Massey, n.d.
    - Hoffman, n.d., [2 items]
    - Charlie Cox and others, 1960
    - "Preacher Cox, G. Jennings and Wife," n.d.
    - Isom Melton, n.d.
    - Unidentified groups (congregations?), n.d., [3 items]
    - Unidentified church interior, n.d.
    - Unidentified churches and congregations, n.d., [3 items]
    - Byllesby Dam site, n.d., [5 items]
    - Matilda Davis and family, n.d.
    - Coleman School construction
  - Population [1790-1970], 1974, n.d. (Box-folder 6-3)
  - Post offices, n.d. (Box-folder 6-4)
  - Printed materials, 1955-1984, n.d., [5 folders] (Box-folder 6-5)
    - Tobler, Viola Haynes. Carroll County Memories, 1890-1920. Wytheville, VA: Jim Presgraves - Books, 1984
    - Virginia Division of State Planning and Community Affairs. Data Summary: Carroll County and Galax City. Richmond, VA: The Division, 1972
    - Descendants of Solomon Cox of Cole Creek, Va. and Other Early Cox Ancestry of the Cole Creek Coxs. [S.l.: s.n.], 1955
    - [Taliaferro, Hardin E.] Fisher's River Scenes. [S.l.]: John Allen Snow, 1958
    - Allison, Edward Ragon. From the Steamboat to the Pulpit. [Church Hill, TN: The Author], [1965?]
    - Poole, Munsey M. The Miracle Mountain Minister. [Galax, VA: s.n.], [1967?]
    - Gardner, Rufus S. The James Gardner Memorial, 1758-1968. [S.l.: s.n.], [1968?]
    - Gardner, Rufus L. Tom Dooley: the Eternal Triangle. Mt. Airy, NC: The Author, 1960
    - Carroll County High School. Reflections. Hillsville, VA: Creative Writing Class, Carroll County High School, 1970-1974, [2 items]
  - Public libraries, 1974-1982 (Box-folder 6-6)
  - Railroads, 1980-1986 (Box-folder 6-7)
  - Roads and bridges, 1972-1982, n.d. (Box-folder 6-8)
  - Ruston land grant, 1974, n.d. (Box-folder 6-9)
  - Schools, 1954-1985, n.d. (Box-folder 6-10)
  - "Southwest Corner" newspaper column, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 6-11)
  - Stone, Thomas J., 1973, n.d. (Box-folder 6-12)
  - Thomas, Moses, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 6-13)
  - Worrell, 1974-1984 (Box-folder 6-14)
- Oversize Materials
  - Alfred C. Meadows / Dalton Hill Christian Church meeting broadside, n.d. (Box-folder 7-1)
  - "45th Annual Old Fiddler's Convention" newspaper supplement, 1980 (Box-item 7-2)
  - "46th Annual Old Fiddlers' Convention" newspaper supplement, 1981 (Box-item 7-3)
  - Carroll News Bicentennial Edition, 1976 (Box-item 7-4)
  - "Mountain Life: a Composite History of the Twin-County Area" (Galax Gazette supplement, 1980-1987, [9 items] (Box-item 7-5)
  - "75th Anniversary of Galax 1906-1981 Commemorative Edition," [1981?] (Box-item 7-6)
  - "Waddell Nursing Home Twentieth Anniversary" ( Galax Gazette supplement, 1985 (Box-item 7-7)
  - "Achieving the Impossible" [Twin County Community Hospital] Galax Gazette supplement, 1988 (Box-item 7-8)
  - Early 20th century newspapers (5 individual issues) (Folder 1)